黑客们好，欢迎来到一场精彩的讲座
hello hackers welcome to yet another awesome lecture
我希望是一个精彩的讲座
hopefully I mean maybe it'll be awesome
继续讲动态分配器误用模块
in the Dynamic Allocator Misuse module
今天我们讨论堆元数据破坏
today we're talking about heap metadata corruption
你已经学过了堆元数据
you've Learned about heap metadata
你已经看到了一些轻微的破坏方式
you've seen ways that some mild corruption
还有tcache可能导致的问题
and tcache can lead to problems
我们要深入挖掘疯狂而又微妙的破坏技巧
we are going to dig so deep into insane crazy subtle corruption techniques
我将在本视频中概述其他类型的元数据破坏
I'll give you an overview in this video of other types of metadata corruption
包括过去的和现在的
historical and present
然后整合起来
and then we'll wrap it up
然后将着手解决一些希望很棒的
and you will tackle the awesome hopefully awesome
为你们准备好的习题
challenge problems will be prepared for you
它们有助于你们学习堆误用
for you to learn about heap misuse
好了，我们开始吧
all right let's roll
先考虑一下
so let's think about
攻击者破坏堆元数据的目标是什么？
the goals of an attacker when they are corrupting heap metadata
通常攻击者破坏堆元数据
generally an attacker corrupts heap metadata
要么是为了通过修改任意内存
to either modify arbitrary memory
滥用堆
like abuse the heap
欺骗堆
fool the heap
让堆认为改动后的内存是堆的元数据
into modifying some memory thinking that it is some other part of heap metadata
可以想象一下
you can imagine
要实现这样的事
doing something like that with
可以通过注入修改tcache中的next指针
injective with modifying that next pointer in tcache
这个我们在上节课中讨论过
as we discussed in the tcache lecture
或者更通用的
or more generally
用的更多的
much more frequently trying to achieve
被称为重叠分配的方法
what is called an overlapping allocation
你对堆做了些操作
so you do something to the heap
把堆搞懵了
and it gets confused
导致堆返回了同一个指针两次
and either returns the same pointer twice
或者返回了一个内存块，但它在已分配内存块内部
or returns one allocation that is actually inside another allocation
或者返回一个栈上的内存
or returns an allocation that actually points to the stack
这些都有可能
all of this is possible
其实你已经看过
and you've actually saw
返回相同内存块两次的场景
the scenario of returning the same allocation twice
在讲tcache那堂课上
again at that tcache lecture
我们利用了双重释放
where we abused the double free
好了，基本的思想
all right and basically the ideas
这两种方法通常都不能给你直接的控制权
of course neither of these typically give you immediate control
但能让你
but they allow you to
进一步破坏程序环境
further break the program's environment
当获得更多控制权
and as you further control
当你对程序内部状态有了更多控制权
you achieve more and more control over a program's internal state
你就可以操纵它
you can slowly begin to puppet it
让它做你想做的事
and get it to do what you want it to do
好吧
all right
我们再来一次
so let's roll again
无论是历史上的还是生活上的
Both historic and in life part historic
我们将从所谓的断连攻击开始
we'll start with something called the Unlink Attack
回忆一下之前讲的chunk的双链表元数据
recall the doubly linked list chunk metadata from the previous video
我把我的视频关一下
I'm going to turn off my video for this one
它盖住ppt上的文本了
because it's overlapsed the text alright
回想一下,
recall that
每个双链表都有前向和后向指针
each the doubly linked list has forward and backwards pointers
当你删除双链表中的chunk时
and when you are removing a chunk from a doubly linked list
比如，删除large bin中的chunk
for example from a large bin
首先查看前一个chunk的后向指针
you will look at the chunk forward of the previous chunk
把它置为当前chunk的后向指针
and you will set its back address to the chunk behind your chunk
然后把后面chunk的前向指针
and you will set the forward address of the chunk behind your chunk
置为当前chunk的前向指针
to the chunk in front of your chunk
演示一下效果更好
this is better actually shown than described
我来演示一下
let me show it to you
好，考虑一下这个场景
all right consider this scenario where
有3个chunk
we have three allocations
A、B、C
we have chunk A chunk B and chunk C
这里只画了前向指针和后向指针
I just displayed the forward and back pointers here
双链表依次是chunk A、chunk B然后是chunk C
and the doubly link list goes chunk a then chunk B then chunk C
现在想要删除chunk B
and we want to remove chunk B
首先找到chunk B
when we do that of course we start with chunk B
看看前面的块，
we look at what is ahead and we say okay
获取B前面的chunk
we take what's ahead
再获取B后面的chunk
we take what is behind
然后把它们连接起来
and we just hook them up
好了，B就被删掉了
boom and chunk B has been removed from the list
使用这两条内存操作语句
using these two memory operations
chunk->fd->bk = chunk->bk;
chunk forward backwards equals chunk backwards
chunk->bk->fd = chunk->fd;
and chunk backwards forwards equals chunk forwards
很明显
obviously
如果覆盖了前向指针和后向指针
you can see if we overwrite the values of chunk forward and chunk backward
或者让前向指针和后向指针指向
or the forward and backwards pointers are
已经被删除了的“鬼”块中
one of the Jason chunks  that you know it is removing itself from
我们可以控制
we can control
内存写操作的目标
the target of these memory write operations
这曾经是一种非常强大非常常见的攻击
this used to be an extremely powerful and extremely common attack
在libc中对此添加了额外的检查
extra checks in libc
这就是安全与性能关系模型的一个例子
this is an example of that cyclic pattern of security and performance
增加了额外的检查
extra checks have been added
以确保chunk链表是正常的
to make sure that the chunk list makes sense
主要看你操作的这一段
the part of the list that you're operating on
那个
that all of the
你前一个chunk的后向指针指向你
the next chunk is pointing back at you
你后一个chunk的前向指针也指向你
and the previous chunk is pointing forward at you
你是要被删的那个chunk
you being the chunk that is being removed
试图解决unlink问题
to try to fix these sort of problems
然而
however
在某些情况下，你仍然可以绕过这些检查
you can still pass these checks in certain scenarios
后面有一个shellphish的"如何堆利用"的链接
I'll have a link to shellphish's how to heap example repository later
我记得在之前的视频中提到过
and I think I mentioned in a previous video
在那个仓库里
over in that repository
有一个现代攻击的例子
they have an example of a modern attack that
它绕过了这些防御
that can bypass some of these defenses
好吧，这是一个过时攻击手法
all right so that's a historical attack
这是一种
one historical attack
另一种历史攻击是一种非常简洁的堆漏洞利用
another historical attack is a really neat heap flaw exploitation
称为空字节投毒
called the poison null byte
好的，问题是
right so the the question is
如果你只有
what if all you have is
一种字符串终止错误
is a kind of a string termination error
或者off by one空字节
or something you know off by one null byte
这种情况发生的次数没有很夸张
this happens not like an insane amount
但发生的次数也不少
but it does happen quite a decent amount
实际上
it was actually
这项技术是根据真实情况开发的
this technique was actually developed based on a real situation
如果我没记错的话
if I remember correctly
这是由Google Project Zero推广的
this was first popularized by Google Project Zero
但不确定
but don't call ?? that
只是突然想到好像是这样的
that's just floating to my mind
如果遇到了下面这种情况
so what if you have something like this
能用null覆盖一个字节
where you have a single byte null byte overwrite
并且只有这个
and that is it
那么问题是什么呢
so what is the problem here
问题实际上是……我的幻灯片不对
the problem actually is that... my slide isn't correct
等一下，让我快速修好它
one second let me fix it real quick
改了什么呢？
all right what changed
改了这里
well what change was that
我将malloc 0x1000更改为malloc 0x1008 //应该改错了，应该是read(0, buf, 0x1008)
I changed the malloc 0x1000 to malloc 0x1008
为什么?我这么做是因为
why? I did this because um
如果你还记得上节课的内容
if you recall from the previous lecture when the
这多的8字节将重用下一个块的prev_size
that extra 8 bytes is going to be the reuse of the next chunk's prev_size
因为当前的块正在使用中
since our current chunk is in use
下一个块的prev_size被用作额外的用户内存
the next chunk's prev_size is actually there for us to use as extra memory
所以当可以溢出一字节
and so when we have this one byte overflow
这个null覆盖的是
what we're actually overflowing with an null byte is
下一个chunk的size
the size value of the next chunk
这就是弱点所在
and that is where the weakness happens
这是对这次攻击的解释图
this is a graph from an explanation of this attack
我会尽我所能地遵循这一点
and I'll try to follow this as as well as I can
它过时了
it's historical
所以它
so it it
现在已经被打上了补丁
you know has now been patched in libc
有很多
there was a quite a lot of
我记得有很多有趣的方法可以绕过这个补丁
I think actually there are interesting ways to still bypass that patch and
让我移动一下视频，这样你们就能看到图形来源
let me move my video so you can see the figure source
可以绕过补丁，继续进行攻击
to bypass that patch and to still carry out this attack
但是对于我们这个模块来说
but but for the purposes of our module
我将谈论没有任何防范的历史攻击手法
I'll be talking about the historical attack without any checks to prevent it
基本上
basically
假设有三个挨着的内存块
imagine you have three allocations right up against each other
先释放了中间的chunk
um and you free the middle one
对，所以，所以
right so so the the
中间的内存块是空闲的
the middle allocation is now a free chunk
它的size变量还在，值是0x208
it still has a size and that size is 0x208
然后你用0覆盖它的部分size
and you overflow into that chunk with your null byte
原来的0x208
and you overwrite 0x208
因为是小端序，变成了0x200
because it's a little endian to 0x200
好的
right
有趣的是
an interesting thing that happens is that when
B是空闲的
so B is free
这意味着C的prev_size是被分配器用着的
that means C's prev_size is being used
如果你回想一下之前的视频
if you recall from the previous video
当你再分配一些内存
when you allocate more
它会分配在B中
it create more allocations to fill up B part by part
分配一些小的内存块
you make small allocations
C的prev_size应该会被更新
C's prev_size should be updated
但是因为B的大小被改小了0x8字节
but because b's size is too small
所以实际上更新的是这里
what is actually updated is some data right here
就在C的prev_size之前
right before C's prev_size
所以C一直认为
so C is constantly saying hey
在我身后有一个大小为0x208的空闲块
behind me there is a size 0x208 free chunk right
当释放B1时
when you free the first filler allocation chunk
它
it
得到
gets
当释放B1
when you free the this allocation chunk ,the filler B
然后释放C
and then you free C
当C被释放时
and when C is freed
它发现自己后面的chunk是空闲的
it says hey is the chunk behind me free
如果它后面的chunk是空闲的。它会合并
and if the chunk behind it is free. it consolidates
它将自己和后面的chunk合并了
it merges the chunk behind it and the chunk itself
并将合并的空闲块添加到unsorted bin中
and adds that to the unsorted bin as a consolidated free chunk
在这个过程中
and in this process
libc忘了原来的chunk B
we forget all about the old allocation B
B2还是一个在用的内存块
that is still a valid allocation
但堆已经忘记了它
but the heap has forgotten about it
下次分配的时候
and next time something is allocated
它会分配B
it will get allocated over B
没错，这是一个很酷的攻击手法
right so this is an awesome attack
仍然有一些方法可以绕过该攻击检查
I think there are still bypasses of checks against this attack
如我所说
like I said
它的历史是丰富多彩的，有补丁被写出
there's a colorful history of patches being written
争论了很长时间
argued over for a long time
libc的邮件列表、代码合并
and the mailing list of libc merged
补丁又被绕过了
immediately bypassed
再出补丁，等等，等等
repatched et cetera et cetera
非常有趣
very fun
算是历史奇事
sort of historical oddity
好吧
all right
来谈谈我最喜欢的堆利用技术
let's talk about my favorite heap technique
The House of force
不幸的是，现在也打了关于它的补丁
it is also now patched unfortunately
但曾经有一段时间
but it there used to be a time
你可以破坏wilderness的大小
when you could corrupt the size of the wilderness
回想一下上节课的wilderness
recall the wilderness from last lecture
它表示堆中还剩下多少字节
it just says how many bytes are there left in the heap
如果你分配的比这个多
if you allocate more than that
它会调用brk来扩展堆内存
then it'll use brk to expand the memory
或者它会mmap一块内存
or it will give you an mapped piece of memory instead
曾经你可以很轻松的
but it used to be that you could simply
用一个超大的数字覆盖wilderness
overwrite that wilderness with a ginormous number
实际上用负数就行，因为计算机存的补码
in fact a negative number right in 2's complement
所以当你
so that when you
这样你就能分配那么多内存
and then you could allocate that much memory allocate
堆就懵了
so that the heap got confused
过多就绕回堆的开头了（可能用了取余）
and went all the way around
这样就能分配之前的内存了
and you could allocate previous
下一次将在堆的较早位置分配内存
your next allocation would be earlier in the heap
或者你可以用一个特定的值覆盖它
or you could update so much memory
这个值可以根据栈和堆的位置算
if you knew where the stack and the heap both were
那么你可以在栈上分配堆的chunk
that you could then allocate chunks onto the the stack
这很酷
this is very cool
我很喜欢使用这种技术，但不幸的是
I really enjoyed using this technique but unfortunately
或者从安全的角度，幸运的是
or fortunately for security
它被打了补丁
it got patched alright
我们来看一个没有打补丁的
let's find one that is not patched
现存（2020年）的一个相关技巧
that is still a very relevant extant technique
the house of spirit
如果你的记忆力很好
if you have a very good memory
你应该还记得这是最初的house系列
you'll recall that this is one of the original houses
是由Phantasmal Phantasmagoria提出的
that were proposed by Phantasmal Phantasmagoria
在他们的SecDev帖子中描述的
described by them in their SecDev post
这开创了house of xxx系列堆利用技术
that kind of created this lore of house of blah or heap techniques
这个想法很简单
the idea is very simple right
事实证明，在free内存时做的校验很少
turns out there are very few checks done at free time
现在仍然是这样
and this is actually still the case
15年前是这样
this was the case 15 years ago
现在还是
still happening
所以你能做的是
so what you can do is
如果可以控制传递给free的指针
if you can control the pointer that is passed into a free
并且你能把它指向一块你能完全控制的内存
and you can point it at some memory that you fully control
你让这块内存看起来像一个chunk，然后释放它
you can make that memory look like a chunk and free it
这基本上就把它，在当前情况，注入到tcache中了
and basically inject it into  in this case into tcache
以前是注入到fast bin或者其它的
it used to be into a fast bin or whatnot
但现在会注入到tcache中
but now you can inject it into tcache
然后等malloc回来的时候
and later when it is malloc back in
或者说等下次malloc一个合适的大小的时候
or then at the next malloc for the appropriate size
你伪造的那个空闲chunk malloc会返回给你
that your chunk your free chunk will be returned
这很令人激动
which is super exciting
我现在展示给你看
and I will show it to you right now
好吧
all right
所以我
so I
我写了个程序，这里是chunk元数据数据结构
I wrote it up so here's our our chunk metadata
我在这里创建这个结构体
you know I just just created a struct
是为了可以轻松在栈上伪造chunk
so that I could easily allocate it on the stack
这个是伪造的stack_chunk，它在栈上
so this is our stack chunk that that's on the stack
我们malloc一个16字节的内存
so we malloc something that is 16 bytes
在我们毒化之前
and before we do the poison
我先展示正常情况是返回在堆上的
I'll show you that that it returns on the heap
然后我们做了一件神奇的事
and then we do this amazing thing
我们说好吧
we say okay
的
the
我们正确地设置了伪造的chunk
we set the chunk properly
我们假设prev_size为0
we say that there's you know whatever prev_size zero
要设置的更合理一点的话
actually this probably should have been a little more proper
这应该是0x21
this should have been 0x21
因为前一个chunk正在使用中
for previous chunk in use
但这不重要
but it turns out that's not so important
嗯
um
基本上
we basically say
有一个
that there is a
我们创建一个大小为0x20的chunk
we create a chunk with a size of 0x20
申请的16字节用户数据区加上16字节元数据
that is of course of allocation of 16 plus 16 more for the metadata
所以块大小为0x20
results in a chunk size of hex 20
然后我们释放它
and then we free it
我们free了它
and we free it
实际上
actually
我们释放的这个地址
we free it at this address
因为chunk的起始地址在返回给你的内存地址前16字节
right if you recall the chunk is 2 qwords before your memory location
所以我们需要释放这个内存位置
so we need to free this memory location
然后下次malloc的时候
and then the next time we malloc
我们拿回了这个chunk
we get our chunk back
我们来编译一下
so let's compile that
运行它
run it
好的
boom
第一次分配
first allocation
另一个分配只是为了有趣
another allocation just to to get keep things interested
这是我们在堆上做的第一个分配
so this is that first allocation that we made on the heap right here
然后
and then
在我们毒化缓存后
after we poison the cache right here
你可以看到下一次分配
you can see that the next allocation
返回了一个栈上的地址
returns a stack address
我想现在不需要我告诉你
right now I'm sure I don't need to tell you
和栈上地址重叠有多严重
how brutal an overlapping address onto the stack can be
取决于程序如何使用这个地址
depends on how the program uses this address
如果你
but if you
例如，如果它是一个名称字段
for example if it was a name field
你可以写任意值
that you could just write arbitrarily
你可以用这个方法
you could use this
覆盖栈
then override the stack
覆盖栈帧，溢出返回地址
override the stack frame overflow the return address
然后控制整个程序
and take control of the program
在适当的情况下，这是一个非常强大的技巧
this is a very powerful technique with the right circumstances
如果你能控制这个注入到空闲缓存中的指针
if you can control this pointer that you inject into free
把它指向一个你能控制的地址
and pointed somewhere at data that you control
就ok了
you're good to go
好吧
all right
哦
oops
等一下。技术问题
one second. technical issues
好了，还有一些杂项技巧
alright so a couple of miscellaneous tips I'll leave you with
一个是
one is
有时你处于一种情况
sometimes you're in a situation
你需要触发malloc
where you need to trigger a malloc
但是这个程序中
but the program
就是没有一个可以轻易触发的malloc
just doesn't have a malloc for you to easily trigger
你通常会这样做
you usually do these things
触发堆功能
trigger heap functionality by
通过小心地操纵程序
by kind of puppeting the program carefully
触发程序内部的功能
triggering functionality within that program
让它做你想做的堆操作
to get it to do the heap operations you want done
有时malloc很难触发
sometimes a malloc is hard to trigger
但一些libc函数
well it turns out that some libc functionality
或者其他内部使用malloc的函数
or other functionality internally will use a malloc
例如你可以触发printf
so if you can trigger a printf
传递给它一个足够大的字符串
and pass it a large enough string
它将malloc一个缓冲区，scanf也一样
it will allocate a buffer using malloc same with scanf
设置好了的话
with the right setup
例如，设置了一个重叠
if you for example set up an overlapping
或者毒化tcache
if you poisoned the tcache for example
使用house of spirit，伪造一个栈上的chunk
using house a spirit with a chunk on the stack
然后调用scanf
and then you call scanf
继而调用malloc，然后开始写内存
and that mallocs and starts writing to a buffer
或者printf也行
or printf will do the same thing
你可以直接用printf导致栈溢出
you can directly cause a stack buff overflow  just with that printf
这很酷
now which is super super cool to see
需要注意的是，有时你将使用printf进行调试
one caveat sometimes you're using printf for debugging
你不希望它
and you don't want it to create
调用malloc
to malloc stuff
你可以禁用这个行为
so you can disable that behavior
可以使用这些函数禁用libc内部缓冲
by disabling libc's internal buffers with these functions
好吧
all right
我要提的最后一点
final note I mentioned
欺骗操纵程序去做你想做的事
this sort of tricking puppeting the program to do what you wanted to do
调用想要调用的堆操作
to make the call the heap operations that you wanted to call
很难
this is very hard
你会在作业中发现它到底有多难
and you will find out how hard it really is in the homework
堆利用需要掌握极其精确的堆布局
heap exploitation requires extremely precise heap layout
有自动化方法
there is automation being done in this area
例如最近出现的技术
for example recent publications on techniques
它会自动执行所谓的“堆按摩”
that will automatically do what is called heap massaging
将堆按到正确的位置
massage your heap into the right place
总之掌握它并不容易
but mastering this is not easy
但你们会成为这方面的大师
but you will become masters at it
你将用它获取flag，祝你好运
and you'll use it to get flags good luck